<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
 <title type="text">Live. Die. Live Again.: Live. Die. Live Again.</title>
 <link rel="self" href="http://www.example.com/feeds/all.atom.xml" />
 <link href="http://www.example.com/index.html" />
 <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-index-html</id>
 <updated>2014-09-17T19:53:15Z</updated>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">How to Setup GPG+SSH in KDE</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.example.com/blog/2014/09/17/how-to-setup-gpg-ssh-in-kde/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-blog-2014-09-17-how-to-setup-gpg-ssh-in-kde</id>
  <published>2014-09-17T19:53:15Z</published>
  <updated>2014-09-17T19:53:15Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Rommel Martinez</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When both GPG and SSH are integrated with KDE, it makes inter-operating with those systems very easy. It will make the difference between a loose-fitting glove, and one that fits snugly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This quick tutorial will go over the steps on how to go about it. To accommodate everyone, I&amp;rsquo;ll still go about how to install and configure all the necessary components.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id="prerequisites"&gt;Prerequisites&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chances are, you already have both GPG and SSH installed on your system. But if you don&amp;rsquo;t have them, you can install them with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install gnupg2 ssh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important software that we need to install is pinentry:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt-get install pinentry-qt4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the component that prompts the user for passphrases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="configure-ssh"&gt;Configure SSH&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have the parts in front of us, it&amp;rsquo;s time to assemble them. The first thing that we need to do (although in reality the files that we are going to open in this section can be done in any order that you wish), is create your SSH keys:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh-keygen -t rsa&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DO NOT&lt;/strong&gt; leave the passphrase empty. Shoot yourself first in the  head, if you really want to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above command will create two files: 1) your public key, and 2) your private key. I need not tell you what they are because you know what they are already. Am I right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub
~/.ssh/id_rsa&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, copy your SSH keys to the servers that you manage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh-copy-id user@host&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="configure-gpg"&gt;Configure GPG&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In case you forgot how to your keys, the command is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;gpg2 --gen-key&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should have this earlier, that if you want to create strong passphrases, use the &lt;a href="http://world.std.com/~reinhold/diceware.html"&gt;Diceware method&lt;/a&gt;. An &lt;a href="https://xkcd.com/936/"&gt;XKCD comic&lt;/a&gt; was written in case you&amp;rsquo;re wondering what it is, without reading the earlier link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next thing to do is edit the main GPG config file:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;emacs ~/.gnupg/gpg.conf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the line that contains &lt;code&gt;use-agent&lt;/code&gt; and uncomment it, if it is commented. If that line does not exist just put &lt;code&gt;use agent&lt;/code&gt; at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to edit the agent file next:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;emacs ~/.gnupg/gpg-agent.conf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then put the following lines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;no-grab
default-cache-ttl 10800
default-cache-ttl-ssh 10800
pinentry-program /usr/bin/pinentry-qt4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those are &lt;em&gt;my&lt;/em&gt; preferred values. If you want to change them, look at the manpage first:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;man gpg-agent&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="configure-kde"&gt;Configure KDE&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now need to link the GPG agent with KDE. We&amp;rsquo;re going to create a &lt;em&gt;startup&lt;/em&gt; script for KDE that will invoke the GPG agent at startup. We&amp;rsquo;ll also tell the GPG agent to enable SSH support (in the old days, the SSH agent has to be ran separately from GPG).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mkdir ~/.kde/env
emacs ~/.kde/env/01_gpg-agent.sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then put in the following lines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/sh

killall gpg-agent
eval `gpg-agent --enable-ssh-support --daemon`&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it executable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;chmod +x ~/.kde/env/01_gpg-agent.sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we&amp;rsquo;ll create the &lt;em&gt;shutdown&lt;/em&gt; script for the GPG agent:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;mkdir ~/.kde/shutdown
emacs ~/.kde/shutdown/01_gpg-agent.sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then put in the following lines:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/sh

killall gpg-agent&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also make it executable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;chmod +x ~/.kde/shutdown/01_gpg-agent.sh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="verification"&gt;Verification&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, we have to restart our KDE session to take these settings into effect. If you how to make them work, without logging out, please let me know in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Press &lt;code&gt;Ctrl+Alt+Del&lt;/code&gt; to logout, then login with your account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open a Konsole window, then connect to your favorite SSH server:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ssh user@remotehost&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A pinentry dialog box should appear prompting you for your passphrase. This passphrase will be cached according to your settings in &lt;code&gt;~/.gnupg/gpg-agent.conf&lt;/code&gt;. Subsequent SSH connection attempts will not prompt you for the passphrase within this timeout period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar behavior will happen if you encrypt a file with GPG:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;gpg2 -s -e -a -r john@remotehost file.dat&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The steps outline above are meant to be succinct without going through the gory details. I avoided reiterating what was already said before so as not to bore you to death. If you found this useful, feel free to comment below.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">An Introduction to Ugarit</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.example.com/blog/2014/02/21/an-introduction-to-ugarit/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-blog-2014-02-21-an-introduction-to-ugarit</id>
  <published>2014-02-21T12:07:18Z</published>
  <updated>2014-02-21T12:07:18Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Rommel Martinez</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many times have we experienced hindsight, after a catastrophic event has happened? how many times have we told ourselves that had we created backups of our precious data, we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be in that dire situation, pulling our hairs out like a maniac?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us have been there &amp;mdash; we lost our precious files due inadvertent causes. We lost them because of disk crash, data corruption, security breach, and other reasons. But had we created a fallback, a big, safe foam that we can land on, it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have been a lot of trouble, and heart ache. On the flip side, creating and managing backups can be daunting, and equally dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll talk about &lt;a href="http://www.kitten-technologies.co.uk/project/ugarit/doc/trunk/README.wiki"&gt;Ugarit&lt;/a&gt; , a nice piece of technology, that combines ease-of-use, and security, in a single tool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ugarit is a classic example of a tool, that requires minimal setup and configuration, but is used many times. That once the initial tinkering is done, all we need to do is reuse the tool. But that isn&amp;rsquo;t Ugarit&amp;rsquo;s main strength &amp;mdash; it is the almost unholy marriage of convenience and security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most, if not all the time, convenience is inversely proportional to security. That is, the more convenient something is, the less secure it is. With Ugarit, creating and managing backups is as easy as typing a short command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="installation"&gt;Installation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we need to install &lt;a href="http://www.call-cc.org/"&gt;Chicken&lt;/a&gt;. Most likely, it can be installed via your package manager:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get install chicken-bin&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it isn&amp;rsquo;t available on your system, you may download it from &lt;a href="http://code.call-cc.org/"&gt;code.call-cc.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Chicken is installed, let&amp;rsquo;s install Ugarit itself, and some dependencies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ chicken-install -s ugarit tiger-hash aes&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After this command completes, the command &lt;code&gt;ugarit&lt;/code&gt; will become available. To display command-line help:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ugarit -h&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="configuration"&gt;Configuration&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ugarit at this point isn&amp;rsquo;t usable yet &amp;mdash; we need to specify where will it store the snapshots. When creating a snapshot of a directory several terabytes big, it is ideal to store the data on a fast, reliable, stress-tolerant disk. It is not uncommon for the command &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; to experience a noticeable lag when ran inside the data directory. Let&amp;rsquo;s presume that &lt;code&gt;/dev/sdb1&lt;/code&gt; is a large filesystem and we want to mount it to &lt;code&gt;/ugarit/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo mkdir /ugarit
$ sudo mount /dev/sdb1 /ugarit
$ sudo mkdir /ugarit/vault
$ sudo chown -R $USER /ugarit&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another, equally important requirement that we need to have is its config file, usually named &lt;code&gt;ugarit.conf&lt;/code&gt;. It is supplied as part of the required command line arguments. It is important to note, that this file does not reside in a fixed location, in contrast with some programs that look for a config file at start-up, from &lt;code&gt;~/&lt;/code&gt;. But before we actually create that file, we need to run some commands. Save the outputs of these commands, because we&amp;rsquo;ll be needing them later:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a salt, for the hash function:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ dd if=/dev/random bs=1 count=64 2&amp;gt;/dev/null | base64 -w 0 | tail -1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create the key, for the vault:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ dd if=/dev/random bs=32 count=1 2&amp;gt;/dev/null | od -An -tx1 | tr -d ' \t\n'&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After we run those commands, we&amp;rsquo;ll create the config file, &lt;code&gt;ugarit.conf&lt;/code&gt;. To make it consistent with the example above, we&amp;rsquo;ll store it inside &lt;code&gt;/ugarit&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ emacs /ugarit/ugarit.conf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then input the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(storage "backend-fs fs /ugarit/vault")
(file-cache "/ugarit/cache")
(hash tiger "SALT")
(encryption aes "KEY")&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replace SALT, and KEY, with the salt and key strings that we generated above. Save the file, then secure it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ chmod 600 /ugarit/ugarit.conf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="basic-usage"&gt;Basic Usage&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id="creating-snapshots"&gt;Creating Snapshots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create a snapshot, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ugarit snapshot /ugarit/ugarit.conf TAG DIRECTORY&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TAG&lt;/strong&gt; is a name that you will identify the snapshot with later, while &lt;strong&gt;DIRECTORY&lt;/strong&gt; is the filesystem tree that you will create a snapshot of. To create, for example, a snapshot of the directory &lt;code&gt;pictures/&lt;/code&gt;, with the tag &lt;code&gt;pix&lt;/code&gt;, run Ugarit like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ugarit snapshot /ugarit/ugarit.conf pix pictures&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the snapshot, you&amp;rsquo;ll see similar to the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Archiving pictures to tag pix...
Root hash: ddc888c86db6d7c468a27cc4af9b2907d219936df82e0971
Successfully snapshotted pictures to tag pix
Snapshot hash: ab290399f31fff1e3158c0ede8f90f59b2b41387af48f597
Written 910460 bytes to the vault in 4 blocks, and reused 0 bytes in 0 blocks
(before compression)
File cache has saved us 1 file hashings / 638104 bytes (before compression)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id="exploring-snapshots"&gt;Exploring Snapshots&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To interactively manage the contents of the vault, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ugarit explore /ugarit/ugarit.conf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To list the available commands:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; help&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking hints from the help usage, we&amp;rsquo;ll extract a directory, that was part of the snapshot earlier. Let&amp;rsquo;s say that the original path of that directory was &lt;code&gt;pictures/holiday&lt;/code&gt;. So, to extract the directory &lt;code&gt;holiday/&lt;/code&gt; to the current directory, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; cd pix
/pix&amp;gt; cd current
/pix/current&amp;gt; cd contents
/pix/current/contents&amp;gt; get holiday
Extracted holiday
/pix/current/contents&amp;gt; exit&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id="extracting-snapshots-directly"&gt;Extracting Snapshots Directly&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If, however, you know the exact path to a file or directory that you want to extract, you can instead run Ugarit with the extract mode. To extract the directory &lt;code&gt;holiday/&lt;/code&gt; from above, directly, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ugarit extract /ugarit/ugarit.conf /pix/current/contents/holiday&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="tips"&gt;Tips&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id="remote-filesystems"&gt;Remote Filesystems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ugarit is not limited to creating snapshots of a local filesystem. It can also be used to create snapshots of trees, from a remote host, mounted locally. If you have an &lt;a href="http://fuse.sourceforge.net/sshfs.html"&gt;SSHFS&lt;/a&gt; mount, for example, you can still create a snapshot of it, just like any other local filesystem:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sshfs remotehost:/ ~/mnt/sshfs/remotehost
$ cd ~/mnt/sshfs
$ ugarit snapshot /ugarit/ugarit.conf remotehost&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same applies to &lt;a href="http://www.samba.org/samba/smbfs/"&gt;SMBFS&lt;/a&gt; mounts:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo mount -t cifs -o user=$USER,uid=$USER //winhost/c ~/mnt/smbfs/winhost/c
$ cd ~/mnt/smbfs
$ ugarit snapshot /ugarit/ugarit.conf winhost&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id="miscellany"&gt;Miscellany&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To disable output, when creating snapshots:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ugarit snapshot /ugarit/ugarit.conf -q ...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To enable very verbose output, when creating snapshots:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ugarit snapshot -:a256 /ugarit/ugarit.conf ...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="notes"&gt;Notes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are doubtful of the performance of the disk where you&amp;rsquo;ll be storing the snapshots, disable the &lt;a href="http://linux.about.com/library/cmd/blcmdl1_updatedb.htm"&gt;locate and updatedb&lt;/a&gt; service. It is usually run periodically via cron. It places a lot of load on the disk, and may over-stress it. Your mileage may vary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important caveat worth mentioning is that, due to the way Ugarit works, snapshot deletions do not exist. The storage mechanism works similarly to Git, only that there is no rebase option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ugarit was created by &lt;a href="http://www.snell-pym.org.uk/alaric/"&gt;Alaric Snell-Pym&lt;/a&gt;. If you want to learn more about it, head over to &lt;a href="http://www.kitten-technologies.co.uk/project/ugarit/doc/trunk/README.wiki"&gt;kitten-technologies.co.uk/project/ugarit/&lt;/a&gt;. To report bugs, go to &lt;a href="http://www.kitten-technologies.co.uk/project/ugarit/reportlist"&gt;kitten-technologies.co.uk/project/ugarit/reportlist&lt;/a&gt; .&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">An Introduction To Frog</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.example.com/blog/2014/02/19/an-introduction-to-frog/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-blog-2014-02-19-an-introduction-to-frog</id>
  <published>2014-02-19T14:07:11Z</published>
  <updated>2014-02-19T14:07:11Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Rommel Martinez</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When publishing blog content to the web, most would rely on pre-fabricated services, that do most of the heavy lifting. However, there are instances when we want to have more control over our stuff. A good example of which are the constraints that providers enforce. Another is the presence of ads, or the use of freemium services, i.e., things can be done, only up to a certain visible limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One may argue that all they need is a platform to blog with, and that they don&amp;rsquo;t need the extra flexibility. While that is fine, some of us, including me, want to free from these shackles. I don&amp;rsquo;t want ads on my site. I don&amp;rsquo;t want surprise censorship. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to pay for services that I can get for free. I want freedom. Now, if you&amp;rsquo;re like me, then read on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was looking for tools to create this blog, I became dissatisfied with most of the mainstream options. Some are the just too difficult to setup, while some are lacking in features. I became frustrated because each end of the spectrum forces me to use something that is extremely mediocre in at least one critical aspect. Fortunately, I found &lt;a href="http://github.com/greghendershott/frog"&gt;Frog&lt;/a&gt;, via a suggestion on #racket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frog, in layman&amp;rsquo;s terms, is a site creator, that is very easy to use, configure, and customize. Whatever you write, will appear on your blog &amp;mdash; you get what you expect. There are no weird terms of use, nor arbitrary limits, nor coercion &amp;mdash; it&amp;rsquo;s very close to full control, at the tip of your fingertips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frog operates somewhere in the middle. That is, it looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;Raw content -&amp;gt; Frog -&amp;gt; HTML&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where raw content is either Markdown, Scribble, or HTML source files, or a combination of all. Frog takes in those input files, and it outputs nice HTML that you can upload to your web server. Easy? No, it&amp;rsquo;s even easier that it sounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="installation"&gt;Installation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the succeeding sections, let&amp;rsquo;s presume that your username is &lt;code&gt;john&lt;/code&gt;, and your home directory is &lt;code&gt;/home/john/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To install Frog, we need to install Racket, first. Chances are, your package manager already has it. To install Racket on Debian, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get install racket&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the unlikely event that it can&amp;rsquo;t be installed using your package manager, go to &lt;a href="http://racket-lang.org/download/"&gt;racket-lang.org/download/&lt;/a&gt; , then follow the instructions from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we need to install Frog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ raco pkg install frog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After which, you&amp;rsquo;ll get the &lt;code&gt;raco frog&lt;/code&gt; command. Let&amp;rsquo;s display its help options:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ raco frog -h&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="first-use"&gt;First Use&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sweet. Now that we have Frog installed, let&amp;rsquo;s get rolling. To create your first Frog-powered website, we&amp;rsquo;ll create a project directory first:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ mkdir blog
$ cd blog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll then fire the spark plug, to initialize the site repository:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ raco frog --init&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll see a message saying that your website is ready. Let&amp;rsquo;s follow the suggested command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ raco frog -bp&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What that command does is that it builds the HTML files from the sample source files created with the &lt;code&gt;--init&lt;/code&gt; switch, then it runs a local web server, serving by default, the location &lt;a href="http://localhost:3000"&gt;http://localhost:3000&lt;/a&gt;. Frog will then open a new browser tab, or window, pointing to that URL. The page that you&amp;rsquo;ll see contains the default site layout. When you&amp;rsquo;re OK with it, let&amp;rsquo;s go back to the terminal, and kill that process by hitting &lt;code&gt;C-c&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="creating-new-posts"&gt;Creating New Posts&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a new article from scratch is another easy task:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ raco frog -n "New Blog Post."&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What it does is that it creates a Markdown file, relative to the current directory, with the format &lt;code&gt;_src/posts/YYYY-MM-DD-post-title.md&lt;/code&gt;. With the command above, the absolute path would be similar to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/home/john/blog/_src/posts/2014-02-21-new-blog-post.md&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s edit that file, and see how it looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ emacs _src/posts/2014-02-21-new-blog-post.md&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    Title: New Blog Post
    Date: 2014-02-21T18:53:42
    Tags: DRAFT

_Replace this with your post text. Add one or more comma-separated
Tags above. The special tag `DRAFT` will prevent the post from being
published._

&amp;lt;!-- more --&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind that this file, was created for us, by the command &lt;code&gt;raco frog
-n ...&lt;/code&gt;. The first three lines contains metadata about our post. They&amp;rsquo;re the post title, date of creation, and tags, respectively. The date was picked up from the the &lt;code&gt;-n&lt;/code&gt; switch that was issued, earlier. The &lt;code&gt;Tags&lt;/code&gt; field, contains a comma-separated list of words, that Frog would later identify the post with. When the case-sensitive tag &lt;code&gt;DRAFT&lt;/code&gt; is used, the file will be skipped during the build phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four spaces must be prefixed, prior, to those three lines, followed by an empty line. The rest will be the actual article content, in Markdown format. When a line by its own contain just the text &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;!-- more --&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, that line will be replaced by a hyperlink in the final HTML form, that will point to the rest of the article. That means, all text, after the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;!-- more --&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; line will not appear in the blog index, but will appear in the link for the whole post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say we change that file to look something like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;    Title: New Blog Post
    Date: 2014-02-21T18:53:42
    Tags: arts, history

Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet, consectetuer adipiscing elit. Donec odio. Quisque
volutpat mattis eros. Nullam malesuada erat ut turpis. Suspendisse urna nibh,
viverra non, semper suscipit, posuere a, pede.

&amp;lt;!-- more --&amp;gt;

Donec nec justo eget felis facilisis fermentum. Aliquam porttitor mauris sit
amet orci. Aenean dignissim pellentesque felis.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, run the build command, again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ raco frog -bp&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now have two posts, as displayed in the index. To remove the auto-generated initial post, that was created by the command &lt;code&gt;raco frog --init&lt;/code&gt;, earlier, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ rm -f _src/posts/2012-01-01-a-2012-blog-post.md&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, rebuild the files:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ raco frog -bp&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="customizations"&gt;Customizations&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this time, you&amp;rsquo;re really itching to customize the site. Yep, that&amp;rsquo;s what we&amp;rsquo;re going to do in this section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the basic level, there are three files that we are going to modify, to make our initial changes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;.frogrc&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;_src/page-template.html&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;_src/post-template.html&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;css/bootstrap.css&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;css/bootstrap.min.css&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s examine each of the files in the list, closer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="frogrc"&gt;.frogrc&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This file is where top-level customizations are made. Open the file &lt;code&gt;.frogrc&lt;/code&gt;, located in the current directory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ emacs .frogrc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll notice that there are more than a dozen parameters that can be tweaked. But for now, we&amp;rsquo;re only concerned about three parameters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;scheme/host&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;title&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;author&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;scheme/host&lt;/code&gt; should contain the (sub)domain to which you&amp;rsquo;ll be publishing your work later, &lt;code&gt;title&lt;/code&gt; is the name of your blog, and &lt;code&gt;author&lt;/code&gt; is your name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="page-templatehtml"&gt;page-template.html&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This file contains the common content, across all types of pages, whether they are blog or non-blog posts. Open the file &lt;code&gt;_src/page-template.html&lt;/code&gt;, located in the current directory:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ emacs _src/page-template.html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll see an even bigger file, compared to .frogrc. This is an special HTML file, that contains Racket, and Frog-specific code. It will be used as a basis for all pages that you&amp;rsquo;ll create with Frog. There are plenty of parameters here, but we&amp;rsquo;ll just tweak some that are most usable to us, at the moment. To make it easier, I&amp;rsquo;ll just list down the items to search and replace for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;The Unknown Blogger&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;My Blog Brand&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Welcome&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Your legal notice here&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you get to those respective sections, it should evident what to replace them with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="post-templatehtml"&gt;post-template.html&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similar to &lt;code&gt;page-template.html&lt;/code&gt;, but this file contains content that will only appear with blog posts. It is also Perhaps the easiest file to modify is &lt;code&gt;_src/post-template.html&lt;/code&gt;. Let&amp;rsquo;s open it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ emacs _src/post-template.html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For now, you only need to modify the text &lt;code&gt;shortname&lt;/code&gt;. It is the identifier that links the comments section of your blog posts, to the aforesaid Disqus account. More about this will be discussed in the section &lt;strong&gt;Comments&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="bootstrapcss-and-bootstrapmincss"&gt;bootstrap.css and bootstrap.min.css&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These two files are responsible for what is commonly called as &amp;ldquo;theme&amp;rdquo; &amp;mdash; it controls the look of the site. To change these files, let&amp;rsquo;s head over to &lt;a href="http://bootswatch.com/"&gt;bootswatch.com&lt;/a&gt;, then let&amp;rsquo;s select a theme we like. Let&amp;rsquo;s presume that we want to download the &lt;em&gt;Cerulean&lt;/em&gt; theme. Click the dropdown box arrow, next to the download link, for that theme. Select and download both &lt;code&gt;bootstrap.min.css&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;bootstrap.css&lt;/code&gt;. After which, copy them over to the css subdirectory &lt;code&gt;css/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cp ~/Downloads/bootstrap.*.css css/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="miscellany"&gt;Miscellany&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we created a new post earlier, we used the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;raco frog -n "New Blog Post"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That command, creates a Markdown source file. Frog, however, has another mode &amp;mdash; Scribble. This mode lets you use a Scribble source file, instead. To create one, we&amp;rsquo;ll use the following command:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;raco frog -N "New Blog Post"&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had you used this command earlier, the file will have the format &lt;code&gt;_src/posts/YYYY-MM-DD-post-title.md&lt;/code&gt;. With the command above, the absolute path would look like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/home/john/blog/_src/posts/2014-02-21-new-blog-post.scrbl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, let&amp;rsquo;s edit that file, and see how it looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;emacs _src/posts/2014-02-21-new-blog-post.scrbl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;#lang scribble/manual

Title: New Blog Post
Date: 2014-02-21T18:53:42
Tags: DRAFT

Replace this with your post text. Add one or more comma-separated
Tags above. The special tag `DRAFT` will prevent the post from being
published.

&amp;lt;!-- more --&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re mostly the same, except with the addition of the language specifier, &lt;code&gt;#lang scribble/manual&lt;/code&gt;, and the absence of the prefix spaces for the metadata fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="comments"&gt;Comments&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frog makes use of &lt;a href="http://disqus.com"&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; to handle its comments. To use it, create an account at &lt;a href="https://disqus.com/profile/signup/?next=http%3A//disqus.com/"&gt;disqus.com/profile/signup/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you already have your account, go to &lt;a href="http://disqus.com/admin/create/"&gt;disqus.com/admin/create/&lt;/a&gt; to create a site, which will have an alias called a &lt;em&gt;shortname&lt;/em&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;shorname&lt;/em&gt; is what you&amp;rsquo;ll register with Disqus to uniquely identify your website. So, if you chose, for example, &lt;code&gt;foobar&lt;/code&gt;, as the shortname for the site, you may then access &lt;a href="http://foobar.disqus.com"&gt;foobar.disqus.com&lt;/a&gt; to manage the comments for that site. The shortname mentioned here, is what you&amp;rsquo;ll use in the file &lt;code&gt;_src/post-template.html&lt;/code&gt;, as discussed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To import comments, from an existing blog, to Disqus, go to &lt;a href="http://import.disqus.com"&gt;import.disqus.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="show-time"&gt;Show Time&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To publish your work, upload the contents of the directory that Frog manages; in this tutorial, it is the directory &lt;code&gt;/home/john/blog&lt;/code&gt;, to your remote web server. If the current directory is &lt;code&gt;blog/&lt;/code&gt;, and we want to send the files via rsync, the command would look like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ rsync -avz ./ remotehost:public_html&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The directory &lt;code&gt;public_html&lt;/code&gt; could be something else, I just used it because it is the default with Apache.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you don&amp;rsquo;t have a remote host that you can upload your work to, via rsync, and you use &lt;a href="http://git-scm.com"&gt;Git&lt;/a&gt;, you can use the free hosting service of &lt;a href="http://pages.github.com"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;. If you don&amp;rsquo;t have a GitHub account yet, you may go to &lt;a href="http://github.com"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; to create one. To use, GitHub Pages, create a repository named &lt;code&gt;USERNAME.github.io&lt;/code&gt;. So, if your username is &lt;code&gt;johndoe&lt;/code&gt;, the repository that you need to create should be named &lt;code&gt;johndoe.github.io&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To publish your work to GitHub Pages, we first need to add that remote repository:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git remote add origin git@github.com:johndoe/johndoe.github.io.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we push the commits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git push origin master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To view your website, go to &lt;a href="http://johndoe.github.io"&gt;johndoe.github.io&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="notes"&gt;Notes&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/greghendershott/frog"&gt;Frog&lt;/a&gt; is a viable and usable site creator. It is easy-to-use, highly configurable, flexible, and yes, open source. It gives control, back to the author.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frog was created by &lt;a href="http://www.greghendershott.com/"&gt;Greg Hendershott&lt;/a&gt;. If you want to learn more about it, head over to &lt;a href="http://github.com/greghendershott/frog"&gt;github.com/greghendershott/frog&lt;/a&gt;. To report bugs, go to &lt;a href="https://github.com/greghendershott/frog/issues"&gt;github.com/greghendershott/frog/issues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ribbit!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Emacs and Mail</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.example.com/blog/2014/02/17/emacs-and-mail/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-blog-2014-02-17-emacs-and-mail</id>
  <published>2014-02-17T16:02:38Z</published>
  <updated>2014-02-17T16:02:38Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Rommel Martinez</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in this day and age, checking our mail means going to the website of our mail provider, or using a mobile app. however, there are some cases when we want to have more control over our messages, especially when the feature we want is not present with the mainstream options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;emacs provides a plethora (gnus, wanderlust, vm, etc.) of ways of sending and receiving mail. in this post, we&amp;rsquo;re going to talk &lt;a href="http://pyropus.ca/software/getmail/"&gt;getmail&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.djcbsoftware.nl/code/mu/"&gt;mu&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.djcbsoftware.nl/code/mu/mu4e.html"&gt;mu4e&lt;/a&gt;, and how to set them up quickly. In this tutorial We&amp;rsquo;ll assume that we&amp;rsquo;re going to get our messages from &lt;a href="http://gmail.com"&gt;Gmail&lt;/a&gt; via its IMAP interface.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id="fetching-messages"&gt;Fetching Messages&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We first need to have a way to download our mails, off our mail server. A easy-to-use application that will do that for us is &lt;a href="http://pyropus.ca/software/getmail/"&gt;getmail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="installation"&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the time, getmail can be readily installed via your system&amp;rsquo;s package manager. If you are using a &lt;a href="https://www.debian.org/misc/children-distros"&gt;Debian-based system&lt;/a&gt; , you can install it by running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get install getmail4&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are using &lt;a href="https://nixos.org/nixos/"&gt;NixOS&lt;/a&gt;, you can install by running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ nix-env -i getmail&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if your system doesn&amp;rsquo;t provide an easy way for you to install getmail, you can always head to its &lt;a href="http://pyropus.ca/software/getmail/"&gt;homepage&lt;/a&gt; , then download the tarball.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="configuration"&gt;Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we need to conjure the incantation so that getmail knows how to get your stuff. Create the file &lt;code&gt;~/.getmail/getmailrc&lt;/code&gt;. In addition to that, we need to create and specify where the messages will go:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ mkdir ~/Maildir
$ mkdir ~/.getmail
$ emacs ~/.getmail/getmailrc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then put in the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;[retriever]
type = SimpleIMAPSSLRetriever
server = imap.gmail.com
username = USERNAME@gmail.com
password = PASSWORD

[destination]
type = Maildir
path = ~/Maildir/

[options]
verbose = 2
message_log = ~/.getmail/gmail.log
read_all = false
delivered_to = false
received = false&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replace USERNAME with your Gmail username, then replace PASSWORD with your Gmail password. However, if you are using &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/landing/2step/"&gt;2-step authentication&lt;/a&gt;, use an &lt;a href="https://accounts.google.com/IssuedAuthSubTokens"&gt;application-specific&lt;/a&gt; password for the password field. Take note, that &lt;code&gt;~/Maildir&lt;/code&gt; is the default directory that Mail Transfer Agents (MTA) which use the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Maildir"&gt;maildir&lt;/a&gt; format use, to store data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="execution"&gt;Execution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To verify that we can indeed fetch our messages, run getmail:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ getmail&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t choke, and displays something like the following, then you have configured getmail correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;getmail version 4.43.0
Copyright (C) 1998-2012 Charles Cazabon.  Licensed under the GNU GPL version 2.
SimpleIMAPSSLRetriever:foobar@gmail.com@imap.gmail.com:993:
...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="reading-messages"&gt;Reading Messages&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we can download our messages, we need to have a way to read them. This is where mu and the accompanying emacs-based client, mu, comes in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="installation"&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like with getmail above, chances are, mu can be installed via your system&amp;rsquo;s package manager. If you are using a &lt;a href="https://www.debian.org/misc/children-distros"&gt;Debian-based system&lt;/a&gt;, you can install it by running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ sudo apt-get install maildir-utils&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are using &lt;a href="https://nixos.org/nixos/"&gt;NixOS&lt;/a&gt;, you can install by running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ nix-env -i mu&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the above, we need to fetch mu4e. This comes with mu&amp;rsquo;s source code. Download it by running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ mkdir ~/.emacs.d
$ cd ~/.emacs.d
$ git clone git@github.com:djcb/mu.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This creates a &lt;code&gt;mu/&lt;/code&gt; directory in the current directory, which happens to be the default location from which emacs looks for init files. Take note, that the git command above actually fetches the source code of mu, and we can actually use it to install mu. But since, you have your package manager, we&amp;rsquo;ll ignore that. Also the location from which the &lt;code&gt;mu/mu4e/&lt;/code&gt; subdirectory exists from the package manager&amp;rsquo;s installation, varies between systems. So, for now, we&amp;rsquo;re only interested with the &lt;code&gt;mu/mu4e/&lt;/code&gt; subdirectory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="configuration"&gt;Configuration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now need to make that mu4e directory accessible to emacs. To do so, we need to edit either &lt;code&gt;~/.emacs.d/init.el&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;~/.emacs&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ emacs ~/.emacs.d/init.el&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then add the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(setq load-path (append load-path '("~/.emacs.d/mu/mu4e")))
(require 'mu4e)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally we need to put in some information about us, so that emacs won&amp;rsquo;t bother asking us about those details later on:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(setq user-full-name "Foo B. Baz"
       user-mail-address "foo@bar.baz")&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make our life even easier, we&amp;rsquo;ll set some variables:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(setq mu4e-get-mail-command "getmail"
      mu4e-update-interval 300
      mu4e-attachment-dir "~/Downloads")&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2 id="execution"&gt;Execution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can restart emacs so that those settings can take effect, or alternatively, you can mark (C-space) those lines, then hit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;M-x eval-region&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, you can now use mu4e, by hitting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;M-x mu4e&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll get a sexy menu, wherein you can hit shortcuts to get you to where you want. To compose a message, hit &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt;, fill in the fields, then hit &lt;code&gt;C-c C-c&lt;/code&gt; to send the message. The rest of the commands should be self-explanatory, but if you want to learn more, you can read the nice &lt;a href="http://www.djcbsoftware.nl/code/mu/mu4e/index.html"&gt;mu4e manual&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="encryption"&gt;Encryption&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optionally, you may want to add some tweaks so that encryption and decryption of messages, will be easier. This is actually one of my primary reasons why I&amp;rsquo;m using mu4e &amp;mdash; it has been pointed out to me that despite using browser extensions like &lt;a href="http://getfiregpg.org/s/home"&gt;FireGPG&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/its-all-text/"&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s All Text!&lt;/a&gt;, the supposedly private message that you composed got auto-saved by default to the &lt;em&gt;Drafts&lt;/em&gt; folder. This implies, that your unencrypted message, was still saved somewhere. Ahem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make use of these cryptographic utilities, edit your emacs init:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ emacs ~/.emacs.d/init.el&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then add the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(require 'mml2015)
(require 'epa-file)

(defun encrypt-message (&amp;amp;optional arg)
  (interactive "p")
  (mml-secure-message-encrypt-pgp))

(defun decrypt-message (&amp;amp;optional arg)
  (interactive "p")
  (epa-decrypt-armor-in-region (point-min) (point-max)))

(defalias 'ec 'encrypt-message)
(defalias 'dc 'decrypt-message)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mark those lines, then hit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;M-x eval-region&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make the settings take effect, immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To send an encrypt a message, hit &lt;code&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; from the main menu of mu4e, fill in the usual fields like &lt;code&gt;To:&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;Subject:&lt;/code&gt;, then on the message body, hit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;M-x ec&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will tag your outgoing message to be signed and encrypted. To send the it, hit &lt;code&gt;C-c C-c&lt;/code&gt;. This will then prompt you to input your passphrase. It will also ask you to fill in some information regarding your outgoing mail server (SMTP). The SMTP server for Gmail is &lt;em&gt;smtp.gmail.com&lt;/em&gt;, then use &lt;code&gt;USERNAME@gmail&lt;/code&gt;.com when prompted for the username. Use your regular password, when prompted, or input your application-specific password, as described earlier. These information will be saved to &lt;code&gt;~/.authinfo&lt;/code&gt;, and will be used for later messages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To decrypt a message, open the message, then hit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;M-x dc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will prompt you to input your passphrase. After which, you&amp;rsquo;ll be prompted if you&amp;rsquo;ll want to replace the contents of the buffer, say yes to this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These approaches are not fool-proof, because there&amp;rsquo;s at least two gaping holes that you have to be aware of &amp;mdash; emacs backups, and mu4e drafts. With the former, when you are using emacs&amp;rsquo; backup facility, or a package like &lt;a href="http://www.emacswiki.org/emacs/BackupDirectory"&gt;backup-dir&lt;/a&gt;, messages that you compose, presumably before you encrypt it, will have an unencrypted copy to the local disk. With the latter, the same principle applies. So be wary of these situations, and tweak your configuration, as necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind that I purposely avoided fleshing out many details, as it would conflate the attempt of this article to make things simple. However, if you want to learn more, you can always go to the &lt;a href="http://pyropus.ca/software/getmail/documentation.html"&gt;getmail&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.djcbsoftware.nl/code/mu/mu4e/index.html"&gt;mu4e&lt;/a&gt; documentation, to fill in missing gaps, that you may have.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Emacs and Racket</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.example.com/blog/2013/09/29/emacs-and-racket/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-blog-2013-09-29-emacs-and-racket</id>
  <published>2013-09-29T22:21:19Z</published>
  <updated>2013-09-29T22:21:19Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Rommel Martinez</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll discuss the easiest approach that I took to setup up a &lt;a href="http://racket-lang.org"&gt;Racket&lt;/a&gt; development environment on Emacs. Take note, that this is not the only approach available &amp;mdash; some did it in arguably better ways. In this article, I&amp;rsquo;ll try to explain the shortest route that I took.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editing Racket code with Emacs has traditionally been done by rudimentary modes that mostly lacked flexibility. They were able to evaluate current definitions, last definitions, and entire buffers, for the most part. Unfortunately, that didn&amp;rsquo;t suffice with the way Racket dealt with things. A more intelligent way of handling code, was needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, we have &lt;a href="http://www.nongnu.org/geiser/"&gt;Geiser&lt;/a&gt;. To quote the first paragraph on its homepage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
 &lt;p&gt;Geiser is a collection of Emacs major and minor modes that conspire with one or more Scheme interpreters to keep the Lisp Machine Spirit alive. It draws inspiration (and a bit more) from environments such as Common Lisp’s Slime, Factor’s FUEL, Squeak or Emacs itself, and does its best to make Scheme hacking inside Emacs (even more) fun.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I saw several other major modes that tries to do what Geiser does, but I became most comfortable with what Geiser offered. Some similar libraries can co-exist with Geiser, too. I tried those, but it became too complex, for me. I wound up just using Geiser. Also, as a semi-related note, I&amp;rsquo;m using Emacs to edit Racket code because I don&amp;rsquo;t know of any other editor that does it so well. I don&amp;rsquo;t use DrRacket, except when I need to use its nice GUI debugger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="installation"&gt;Installation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My installation method is crude, but it works, at least for me. Other installation methods exist, but I couldn&amp;rsquo;t wrap my brain around them, so I opted instead for something that requires the minimal amount of chore. Also, I&amp;rsquo;m still not sure what are the hidden consequences of not doing it the &amp;ldquo;elegant&amp;rdquo; way, presuming there is one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say that you want to install your Geiser files in &lt;code&gt;~/.emacs.d/elisp/&lt;/code&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll issue the following commands to install Geiser to that location:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ mkdir ~/.emacs.d/elisp
$ cd ~/.emacs.d/elisp
$ git clone http://git.sv.gnu.org/r/geiser.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, in &lt;code&gt;~/.emacs.d/elisp/geiser/&lt;/code&gt;, you&amp;rsquo;ll have something that looks like the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;AUTHORS
autogen.sh*
bin/
ChangeLog
configure.ac
COPYING
doc/
elisp/
.git/
.gitignore
INSTALL
Makefile.am
NEWS
README
README.elpa
scheme/
THANKS&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we want the directory &lt;code&gt;~/.emacs.d/elisp/geiser/elisp/&lt;/code&gt; to be a member of the Emacs variable &lt;code&gt;load-path&lt;/code&gt; so that &lt;code&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; and friends will know where to find things. To do that, add the following to your Emacs init file &amp;mdash; either in &lt;code&gt;~/.emacs.d/init.el&lt;/code&gt;, or in &lt;code&gt;~/.emacs&lt;/code&gt; (deprecated):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(add-to-list 'load-path "~/.emacs.d/elisp/geiser/elisp/")&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we&amp;rsquo;ll put in the actual code that invokes and configures Geiser:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(require 'geiser)

(setq geiser-active-implementations '(racket))

(defun geiser-save ()
  (interactive)
  (geiser-repl--write-input-ring))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first expression loads Geiser, itself. The second one specifies that it won&amp;rsquo;t prompt you for other implementations if it finds them. The last one is optional &amp;mdash; it enables you to execute &lt;code&gt;M-x geiser-save&lt;/code&gt; in the REPL buffer to force saving of the history to the disk file, which is &lt;code&gt;~/.geiser_history.racket&lt;/code&gt;, by default. It is useful if you want to save your REPL session, immediately (Nothing is more horrifying than losing &lt;strong&gt;THAT&lt;/strong&gt; expression). For all the Emacs code above, to take effect, you can evaluate them now using members of the eval-* troupe (&lt;code&gt;eval-defun&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;eval-last-sexp&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;eval-region&lt;/code&gt;), or, you can still opt to respawn a new Emacs process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reap what you sowed, create or open a &lt;code&gt;.rkt&lt;/code&gt; file, with at least a proper module declaration. Then hit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;M-x run-geiser&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, boomshakalaka! A new (Emacs) window opens, containing the &lt;code&gt;* Racket
REPL *&lt;/code&gt; buffer. Whatever you can do with the REPL invoked with vanilla command-line &lt;code&gt;racket&lt;/code&gt;, you can also do with this, and more. This major mode is actually Comint mode, under the hood, with hooks to a a Racket process. For those of you who are unfamiliar with Comint mode, it is the same mode that handles &lt;code&gt;M-x shell&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what can we do with it? While editing &lt;code&gt;.rkt&lt;/code&gt; file, here are some of the usual shortcuts that I use (The full list of keys are &lt;a href="http://www.nongnu.org/geiser/geiser_5.html#Cheat-sheet"&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;). Take note, that the description of the keys that I used below, are for myself initially, to help me understand what they do. They may, or may not diverge from the official description, listed on the aforementioned link.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="racket-buffer"&gt;Racket Buffer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;Key&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;What it does&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;C-c C-z&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Switch to the REPL buffer&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;C-c C-a&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Evaluate current buffer, then switch to the REPL buffer&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;C-M-x&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Evaluate current expression&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;C-x C-e&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Evaluate last expression&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;C-c C-r&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Evaluate region&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;C-c C-\&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Insert a λ symbol&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h2 id="repl-buffer"&gt;REPL Buffer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;Key&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;What it does&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;C-c C-z&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Switch to the Racket buffer&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;M-p&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Switch to the previous history item&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;M-n&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Switch to the next history item&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;C-c M-p&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Jump to previous prompt&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;C-c M-n&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Jump to next prompt&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;C-c C-q&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Quit the REPL buffer&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id="conclusion"&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have intentionally skipped many topics from the &lt;a href="http://www.nongnu.org/geiser/"&gt;official document&lt;/a&gt; because it makes it unattractive to people who are averse to reading long blocks of text (ironically, this article may even qualify as one.). The methods described above are by in no way representative of community-advised ways of installing and using Racket with Emacs. Feel free to drop a comment below! Ciao!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Emacs and Dired</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.example.com/blog/2013/09/26/emacs-and-dired/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-blog-2013-09-26-emacs-and-dired</id>
  <published>2013-09-26T17:57:00Z</published>
  <updated>2013-09-26T17:57:00Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Rommel Martinez</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll be focusing on one of the novel ways Emacs handles &lt;em&gt;directory editing&lt;/em&gt;. The directory editor, or &lt;strong&gt;dired&lt;/strong&gt; (pronounced dir-ed, not die-rd), for short, is the Emacs equivalent of a file manager. Whatever you can do with regular file buffers, you can also do it with dired buffers, to a certain extent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To run dired, run emacs on the command line, supplying a directory as its argument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;emacs ~/Desktop/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or, alternatively, you can press &lt;code&gt;C-x d&lt;/code&gt; inside Emacs. If you are currently editing a file, the directory of that file will be presented as the default value in the minibuffer area. Either way, when you hit &lt;code&gt;Enter&lt;/code&gt;, a buffer of the directory will load, that looks like the output of &lt;code&gt;ls -l&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;/home/john/Desktop/foo:
total used in directory 84 available 540767396
-rw-r--r-- 1 john users 5935 Sep 27 18:17 index.html
-rw-r--r-- 1 john users 5944 Sep 27 18:17 index2.html
drwxr-xr-x 3 john users 4096 Sep 26 17:42 pics
drwxr-xr-x 3 john users 4096 Sep 26 05:39 vids&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, now that we have it, what can we do with it? Well, here is a short list of what, we can do with it. Take note, that the keyboard shortcuts in this article are case-sensitive, unless explicitly stated otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="common-commands"&gt;Common commands&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the usual commands that you would use, in a dired buffer. In addition to that, they can operate on single, or multiple items. Using them for multiple items will be explained, next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;Key&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;What it does&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;R&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Rename item(s)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;C&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Copy item(s)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;D&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Delete item(s)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;O&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Change item(s) owner&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;G&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Change item(s) group&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;M&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Change item(s) permission&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;S&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Create symlink&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;T&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Touch item(s), a la `touch`&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;X&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Execute a shell command on item(s)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id="mark-commands"&gt;Mark commands&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These commands perform mark-related operations on items. Creating marks simply means putting a tag on items, so that you can perform the operations in the previous section, on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;Key&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;What it does&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;m&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Mark an item, for the above-listed commands&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;d&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Mark an item for deletion operations&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;x&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Perform actual deletion&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;u&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Unmark a single item&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;U&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Unmark all items&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;t&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Toggle marks between marked and unmarked items&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id="other-commands"&gt;Other commands&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These commands act on their own. They operate on single items, and they don&amp;rsquo;t make use of marks. The &lt;strong&gt;w&lt;/strong&gt; command, however, is an exception.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;Key&lt;/th&gt;
  &lt;th&gt;What it does&lt;/th&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;+&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Create directory&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;^&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Go up, one level, like `cd ..`&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;e&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Edit an item&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;f&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Edit an item&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;v&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;View an item, like `less` or `more`&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;g&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Reload the current directory&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;j&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Jump to an item&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;s&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Change sort order&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;y&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Show file type of item, like `file`&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
 &lt;tr&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;w&lt;/td&gt;
  &lt;td&gt;Copy item name(s) to the clipboard&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h1 id="wdired-mode"&gt;WDired mode&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;BUT&lt;/em&gt;, one of the coolest, and often-overlooked feature of dired is the &lt;strong&gt;WDired&lt;/strong&gt; mode. What it does is that it gives you a decent ability to edit the item names in a dired buffer, just as you would on a typical buffer. To enter wdired mode, hit &lt;code&gt;M-x wdired-change-to-wdired-mode&lt;/code&gt;. The major mode changes from &lt;code&gt;Dired&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;Editable Dired&lt;/code&gt;. You can then rename the files, and directories, with ease. You can even use rectangle and replace functions on them, to make things easier. The changes you have made at this point are not yet saved. To save the changes, press &lt;code&gt;C-c C-c&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that is it for now. Ciao!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Emacs and Hax</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.example.com/blog/2013/09/10/emacs-and-hax/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-blog-2013-09-10-emacs-and-hax</id>
  <published>2013-09-10T13:23:34Z</published>
  <updated>2013-09-10T13:23:34Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Rommel Martinez</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this series of posts, I will be sharing my personal hacks on how I use Emacs for my day-to-day stuff. Most, if not all of the code contained in these posts are excerpts from the respective configuration files that I use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rest of the configuration can be found at &lt;a href="http://github.com/ebzzry/dotemacs"&gt;github.com/ebzzry/dotemacs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(defun delete-forward-char-or-region (&amp;amp;optional arg)
  (interactive "p")
  (if (region-active-p)
      (delete-region (region-beginning)
                     (region-end))
      (delete-forward-char arg)))

(define-key global-map [deletechar] 'delete-forward-char-or-region)
(define-key global-map [del] 'delete-forward-char-or-region)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This command deletes a region if one is active, or deletes the character underneath the cursor. I have this bound to the DEL key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(defun compile-file ()
  (interactive)
  (compile "make -k"))

(define-key global-map [(control ?x) ?c] 'compile-file)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use this command frequently, and I use it from typesetting LaTeX documents, compiling Scribble documents, compiling code, and just about anything that I can use Make with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(defun geiser-save ()
  (interactive)
  (geiser-repl--write-input-ring))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This comes in very handy for me, because sometimes I lose the REPL buffer before the input ring has been saved. When I need to run I execute &lt;code&gt;M-x geiser-save&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(defun my-scheme-mode-hook ()
  (put 'λ 'scheme-indent-function 1)
  (define-key scheme-mode-map [(control ?c) tab] 'completion-at-point))

(add-hook 'scheme-mode-hook 'my-scheme-mode-hook)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also have the above, since I want to align the &lt;code&gt;λ&lt;/code&gt; symbol nicely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(require 'tramp)

(add-to-list 'tramp-remote-path "/var/run/current-system/sw/bin")&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above snippet is applicable only to users of NixOS, since the filesystem tree is deviantly different from &amp;ldquo;regular&amp;rdquo; nixen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(defun other-window-1 (&amp;amp;optional arg)
  (interactive "p")
  (other-window (- arg)))

(define-key global-map [(control left)] 'other-window-1)
(define-key global-map [(control right)] 'other-window)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my favorites, and I may be biased because I&amp;rsquo;m using a &lt;a href="http://www.kinesis-ergo.com/advantage.htm"&gt;Kinesis Advantage keyboard&lt;/a&gt;, wherein the arrow keys are very easy to reach, but nevertheless, YMMV.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(defun find-two-files (orientation directory file1 file2)
  (let ((file-path1 (file-truename file1))
        (file-path2 (file-truename file2)))
    (delete-other-windows)

    (case orientation
      (vertical (progn (split-window-right)
                       (find-file file-path1)
                       (other-window 1)
                       (find-file file-path2)))
      (horizontal (progn (split-window)
                         (find-file file-path1)
                         (other-window 1)
                         (find-file file-path2)))

      (other-window 1))))

(defun find-two-files-vertically (directory file1 file2)
  (find-two-files 'vertical directory file1 file2))

(defun find-two-files-horizontally (directory file1 file2)
  (find-two-files 'horizontal directory file1 file2))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ev () { emacsclient -nw --eval "(find-two-files-vertically \"$(pwd)\" \"$1\" \"$2\")" }
eh () { emacsclient -nw --eval "(find-two-files-horizontally \"$(pwd)\" \"$1\" \"$2\")" }&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two snippets above, for Elisp and Zsh (or your shell), respectively, load two files into an Emacs buffer, oriented horizontally, and vertically, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to load &lt;code&gt;~/test1.txt&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;~/test2.txt&lt;/code&gt; in Emacs, split windows, horizontally, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ ev ~/test1.txt ~/test2.txt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(require 'server)

(unless (server-running-p)
  (server-start))&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This snippet runs the server instance, when it is not running, yet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(defun kill-current-buffer ()
  (interactive)
  (kill-buffer (current-buffer)))

(define-key global-map [(control ?x) (control ?k)] 'kill-current-buffer)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of us have this, but this is my simple, unconvoluted version&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;(defun mark-line (&amp;amp;optional arg)
  (interactive "p")
  (if (not mark-active)
      (progn
        (beginning-of-line)
        (push-mark)
        (setq mark-active t)))
  (forward-line arg))

(define-key global-map [(shift ? )] 'mark-line)
(define-key global-map [(control ?z)] 'mark-line)&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been plenty of times in the past when I needed this function, and I would have to press a long series of keystrokes just to get it down. The above is what I have, instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, that is it for now. Ciao!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Livefrog: A LiveJournal Utility</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.example.com/blog/2013/05/29/livefrog-a-livejournal-utility/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-blog-2013-05-29-livefrog-a-livejournal-utility</id>
  <published>2013-05-29T15:10:34Z</published>
  <updated>2013-05-29T15:10:34Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Rommel Martinez</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am pleased to announce the release of &lt;strong&gt;livefrog&lt;/strong&gt;, a utility I wrote to migrate LiveJournal articles to &lt;a href="http://github.com/greghendershott/frog"&gt;Frog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sources, along with additional information, are located at &lt;a href="http://github.com/ebzzry/livefrog"&gt;github.com/ebzzry/livefrog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;livefrog is a utility written in &lt;a href="http://racket-lang.org"&gt;Racket&lt;/a&gt;, used to migrate LiveJournal posts to &lt;a href="https://github.com/greghendershott/frog/"&gt;Frog&lt;/a&gt;, a blogging platform written in Racket, too. It uses the files dumped by either &lt;a href="http://hewgill.com/ljdump/"&gt;ljdump&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="http://github.com/ceejbot/ljmigrate"&gt;ljmigrate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="installation"&gt;Installation&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;livefrog is available via Racket&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="http://pkg.racket-lang.org"&gt;Planet2&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ raco pkg install livefrog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that doesn&amp;rsquo;t work, you can alternately install by fetching livefrog, and the dependencies, from github&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ git clone https://github.com/jbclements/sxml.git
$ git clone https://github.com/greghendershott/frog.git
$ git clone https://github.com/ebzzry/livefrog.git
$ raco pkg install frog/ sxml/ livefrog/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trailing slashes are important, to tell &lt;code&gt;raco&lt;/code&gt; that you are installing from local directories. Without it, it will try to fetch the sources from the internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="usage"&gt;Usage&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sections contains instructions for creating files suitable for use with Frog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="basics"&gt;Basics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create a Markdown file from the file entry.xml&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ raco livefrog -m entry.xml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That, however, becomes cumbersome if you&amp;rsquo;re going to manage more than a hundred entries. To automatically &amp;ldquo;pick up&amp;rdquo; the files created by ljdump or ljmigrate, and convert them to Markdown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ raco livefrog -am&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bear in mind, though, that ljdump and ljmigrate differ on how the trees for the data are created. ljdump has the following tree format, where USERNAME is your LiveJournal account name:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ljdump/
  build
  ChangeLog
  convertdump.py
  USERNAME/
    L-1
    L-2
    C-2
    L-3
    ...
  ljdump.config
  ljdump.config.sample
  ljdump-gui.py
  ljdump.py*
  README.txt
  TODO&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ljmigrate, on the other hand, uses a different format:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;ljmigrate/
  LICENSE.text
  ljmigrate.cfg
  ljmigrate.cfg.sample
  ljmigrate.py*
  README.md
  README_windows.txt
  TODO
  www.livejournal.com/
    USERNAME/
      entry00001/
        entry.xml
      entry00002/
        entry.xml
        comment.xml
      html/
      metadata/
      userpics/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After creating the Markdown Frog source files, you may now copy them to your Frog source directory, designated at &lt;code&gt;_src/posts/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="comments"&gt;Comments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frog, by default, uses &lt;a href="http://disqus.com"&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt; to handle the comments. To import comments to this platform, we need to generate an XML file that must adhere to Disqus&amp;rsquo; comment import rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create a file, named &lt;code&gt;comments.xml&lt;/code&gt; that will be used for importing comments, to be used with &lt;a href="http://import.disqus.com/"&gt;import.disqus.com&lt;/a&gt;, using &lt;code&gt;foo.bar.com&lt;/code&gt; as the root site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ raco livefrog -s foo.bar.com -c comments.xml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="updating"&gt;Updating&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you installed livefrog using Planet2, you can update it by running:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ raco pkg update livefrog&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if you used the latter method, you may update it by pulling the updates, uninstalling livefrog, then installing it again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ cd livefrog
$ git pull origin master
$ cd ..
$ raco pkg remove livefrog
$ raco pkg install livefrog/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="miscellany"&gt;Miscellany&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce typing, you may optionally create an alias to &lt;code&gt;raco
livefrog&lt;/code&gt; in your shell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sh-like shells:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ echo 'alias livefrog="raco livefrog"' &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.bashrc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Csh-like shells:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ echo 'alias livefrog raco livefrog' &amp;gt;&amp;gt; ~/.cshrc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Replace &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;.cshrc&lt;/code&gt;, with the appropriate init file for your shell.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Usync: A Data Synchronizer</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.example.com/blog/2013/05/21/usync-a-data-synchronizer/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-blog-2013-05-21-usync-a-data-synchronizer</id>
  <published>2013-05-21T19:18:33Z</published>
  <updated>2013-05-21T19:18:33Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Rommel Martinez</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usync is a a site-to-site synchronization tool written in &lt;a href="http://www.scsh.net"&gt;Scsh&lt;/a&gt;. It makes use of &lt;a href="http://www.cis.upenn.edu/~bcpierce/unison/"&gt;Unison&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://rsync.samba.org/"&gt;rsync&lt;/a&gt;, for bi- and uni-directional synchronizations, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sources, along with additional information, are located at &lt;a href="http://github.com/ebzzry/usync"&gt;github.com/ebzzry/usync&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;h1 id="introduction"&gt;Introduction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Site-to-site synchronizations are usually needed, when two locations, which are called sites, in this article, make file updates independently. Let&amp;rsquo;s say the company &lt;strong&gt;Foo&lt;/strong&gt; has two offices. In the first office, they have the accounting, and logistics departments. In the second office, they have the IT, and HR departments. Both have a common &lt;code&gt;/pub&lt;/code&gt; tree, that has subdirectories assigned to each department. Without synchronization, when the first office needs information from the second office, they&amp;rsquo;d have to pull the updates, manually. With synchronization, the first office can access the files from the second office, as if the IT and HR departments, were in the first office. Usync helps to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="basic-usage"&gt;Basic Usage&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To perform two-way synchronization of the directory &lt;code&gt;/pub/yot/ninam&lt;/code&gt;, between the current host, to the hosts &lt;code&gt;tarupam&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;taubetmo&lt;/code&gt;, while preserving the directory structure remotely (take note, that there must be no spaces between the hosts specification, due to the &lt;code&gt;IFS&lt;/code&gt; environment variable, found in most shells):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ usync /pub/yot/ninam/ tarupam,taubetmo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command above will perform two-way synchronization of the diretory &lt;code&gt;ninam/&lt;/code&gt; found under &lt;code&gt;/pub/yot/&lt;/code&gt;, to &lt;code&gt;tarupam:/pub/yot/&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;taubetmo:/pub/yot/&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using our example above, the two-way synchronization system basically tells that if the tree &lt;code&gt;tarupam:/pub/yot/ninam/&lt;/code&gt; contains new and/or updated items, compared with &lt;code&gt;localhost:/pub/yot/ninam/&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;localhost:/pub/yot/ninam/&lt;/code&gt; also happens to have new and/or updated items, then, they will trade updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally, the result is that &lt;code&gt;localhost:/pub/yot/ninam/&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tarupam:/pub/yot/ninam/&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;taubetmo:/pub/yot/ninam/&lt;/code&gt;, are all equal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="semi-advanced-usage"&gt;Semi-advanced Usage&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is also possible to perform synchronization of multiple files, and directories, to remote hosts. To do so, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ usync /pub/yot/ninam/ ~/file.text ~reyn/*.blend tarupam,taubetmo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The command above will perform two-way synchronization of the paths &lt;code&gt;/pub/yot/ninam/&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;~/file.text&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;~reyn/*.blend&lt;/code&gt; to the remote hosts &lt;code&gt;tarupam&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;taubetmo&lt;/code&gt;, using the same directory structuring system described above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to perform one-way synchronization, of the above, like &lt;code&gt;rsync&lt;/code&gt;, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ usync --one-way --prefer-local /pub/yot/ninam/ ~/file.text ~reyn/draft.blend tarupam,taubetmo&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more usage information, run:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ usync --help&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h1 id="caveats"&gt;Caveats&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This program has been used on FreeBSD, hence making the shebang line contain &lt;code&gt;/usr/local/bin/scsh&lt;/code&gt;. Please change it, accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Squandered Relentlessness</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.example.com/blog/2013/05/09/squandered-relentlessness/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-blog-2013-05-09-squandered-relentlessness</id>
  <published>2013-05-09T16:11:03Z</published>
  <updated>2013-05-09T16:11:03Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Rommel Martinez</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a disturbing, and eerie sensation that I feel whenever the damping realization that I am no longer a young child, is observed in my consciousness. The uneasy struggle between learning to let go of my portentous past and my capricious future, grips me, with heavy clench. It is not about the inability to redo gratuitous expenditure of somewhat liberally-provided lax confinements of time, but it is about the unsettling observation that the mindset I previously took for granted, is now something that would require me Atlas strength to even begin to summon. I miss the unrelenting inquisitiveness that I once wielded with ease, to my daily scuffling scores with the hordes of raids of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we move past our zones of comfort, we are filled with eagerness to return back to our own fortified bunkers. We see our own phantasmal doppelgangers, communicating and showing to us what impending atrocities may rise out of the ground, ready to devour us alive. The longer we stay outside, the higher the probability of death. We make ourselves believe our own convictions. We justify through our own uncalibrated scales of what choices to make. Whenever unfamiliar territory is explored, we almost instantly coil ourselves, back, into seemingly intractable forms. We do it because of fear. We do it because we do not like the unfamiliar. We do it because of our affinity and devotion to safety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We complain of the stifling absence of bounty, and yet we voluntarily stop ourselves from making even an inch of movement of a limb towards making the advancement on a prey. We are so romantically in love, with fervor, on the seeking of rationale to our unjustifiable excuses, but we equally seek sound reason. It is even more appalling to see that some of us insidiously advertise illusions of grandeur, with claims of full reprising sensations of the bounty&amp;rsquo;s meat. Our personal biases towards reaching the reward, effectively stops us from actually reaching it. We succumb to the remorseless claims of others, on their failure, effectively rendering us ignorant of the unseen reality. When the number of persons that flock around us, is high enough, according to our personal metrics, we ignorantly instill to ourselves what they buzz to us, and then we impair ourselves and subsequently kill the essence of our individuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As adults, we are taught to restrain ourselves inside cages that we ourselves have built. It is unnerving to see this monstrous act unfold before my short field of view, everyday. We drag ourselves towards solitary confinements of our own barbed rooms. We make ourselves fond of preaching doubt to our fellowmen. And if our own kind does the same, we see feelings of accomplishment. That is not only horrendous, but also unsurprisingly stupid. When we were still young, we reach out to empty space, and create our own discoveries. We find out about things previously untaught to us. We have the willful disregard for danger and authority. We do not care how about the scratches and bruises that we get, as long as we satisfy our wild and insatiable taste for discovery. When fueled by curiosity, we discover yet another realm of possibilities &amp;mdash; we find ourselves immersed in dimensions never before heard or seen, and no matter how much dirt and mud we lather up to our bodies, we did not care. All that mattered to us was to have fun in walking the unending journey of discovery. And yet, we learned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is ironic that just when we think we are already old enough to venture the world unaided by our training wheels, we smother ourselves with mediocre goals of pseudo-discovery. When the curtain is unveiled, we are confronted by an unsettling sight &amp;mdash; we have lost the drive that once propelled us to have insights. We grew afraid to exercise the same techniques and principles we had once as children. We stopped ourselves from making curious inquisitions about what&amp;rsquo;s out there. We have made ourselves feel comfortable with what is served on the institutionalized plates, without the slightest attempt to bolster up to devise questions. The society, which we are all part of, is part of the disease. This very illness is what we have been aiding to develop, from its inception. This unit is what we have been working hard on, to form our own senses of individuality. We wanted to stand out, and yet all we do is just blend in. How can a formidable hunter become so docile that he becomes the prey himself? Why do we throw away our spears when they are all we have to give us the ability to fight back? Our sensibilities have drifted away into black, bottomless pits, which we have all contributed to making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is aggreging to our shoulders, to see that generations after generations, we squander and believe that discoveries should always be made for us, peeled off then fed to our mouths. What have we become as sailors of the stars? Have we given up the drive to motivate ourselves to see what is on the other side of the rainbow? Have we tame ourselves too much, that we became willing to be incarcerated in zoos, for the pleasure of others? Or did we just flush out our sense of power, to make ourselves stand out less, and mix more with the crowd, greatly reducing our distinctiveness when viewed from afar? It seems that, for now, we refuse to answer some questions, yet we retaliate to the idea that we are being interrogated of things deemed to be simpler than high school classroom lessons. But some things are common to us, albeit not all: we are afraid to see how society may react to our actions, no matter how silly or grave our actions may be. But on matters of more weight, we readily blend in, because we do not want rejection. Most of us are more than happy to think and move with the herd, without any forethought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we voluntarily attach to our legs, heavy chains and balls of steel, we should not expect to be able to run around the colosseum with ease. When we dare to explore uncharted territories, without regrets, without dis-enchantments, without the necessity to have another ship propel us forward, we have triumphed.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">Over, Under, and Elsewhere</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.example.com/blog/2013/05/09/over-under-and-elsewhere/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-blog-2013-05-09-over-under-and-elsewhere</id>
  <published>2013-05-09T16:08:36Z</published>
  <updated>2013-05-09T16:08:36Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Rommel Martinez</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our cunning ability for oversight is deridingly high. Whether it may be solving a problem or just trying to be creative. Our impulse to over-engineer is unusually prevalent if our initial expectations are not met. We drag our consciousness to lengths almost unfathomable because we think that if we pour in a lot of thought, the outcome is positively and proportionately high according to our convictions. We complain about our lack of tools. We complain about our lack of resources. Yet, we are astonished and brought to shocking disbelief when someone does it with far less than what our hands have. We disenchant the probability that what we are precisely looking for, is right on our ear. Our ability to dismiss ideal options hulking right in front of us, is appalling. Why do we need to dig an underground tunnel to get in, when all that is needed is to knock?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very disturbing that we unjustifiably position ourselves to unfailingly accept words just because we have been told to assimilate them. We believe that they are truths without making the slightest advance towards ensuring that what you just heard is infallible. It is also disconcerting that for many, if not most, that they&amp;rsquo;d rather take what they have been told, as is, rather than be criticized for raising their hand to ask what could possibly be dubious claims. When we say yes, without giving the slightest amount of thought, we have effectively enveloped ourselves with a cloud-like cushion, that, while it makes everything immediately adjacent from your skin heavenly, we neglect to pursue the intellectual safety and we give ourselves self-approved parachutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a higher note, I also find that a lot of people radically position themselves to absolute positions. We are very fond of inventing and assigning labels among ourselves. We think that by moving ourselves to thought-bunkers, we build assumptions that because of the security that our bunker provides, we have prevailed. From our DNA that provides us with the information that contains the code of what makes us tick, we turn to our brains to store yet more information. These various pieces of information and high in breadth, that our humble DNA can no longer even begin to contain. But alas, what we have in our individual brains is still not enough to house our ever-growing house of knowledge. We needed to find a way to record them outside our bodies, stored somewhere where data retrieval is one of its most critical operations &amp;mdash; we wrote and created records. We began by writing on stones, walls, and anything that would hopefully persist to contain what it must, across generations of readers. We have built colossal libraries, with gargantuan collections of books. With it, we have stored an immense amount of records, far beyond what all the brains of all humans can contain. Then, the libraries became computer databases. We took yet another step in building tower houses of what our ancestors knew, and what we know today. But both by intrigue and disturbance, we see that not even our most advanced technology is able to carefully record, with predictability, our coordinates in space in time, for the past, present, and future. We are in a time wherein we can, with high certainty, tell whether a drinking glass has something in it or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of us persist in delusions that claim to know what they have never ventured, or at the least, observed. It is very disheartening that instead of taking a step back and gaze at the sky for a moment, people instead immerse themselves in wonderland. This very intoxicating habit, harms not an individual, but the whole mankind. When someone tells you that answers to his questions can only be exclusively be answered always by a yes or no, leave him and that he no longer deserve to have your attention again. If you do not know the answer, you should say that you do not know the answer, instead of doing trapeze jumps without anyone to catch your hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oftentimes, we overlook that all the tools that we need are right with us.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry>
 <entry>
  <title type="text">The Y Combinator in Six Easy Steps</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="http://www.example.com/blog/2013/05/09/the-y-combinator-in-six-easy-steps/?utm_source=all&amp;utm_medium=Atom" />
  <id>urn:http-www-example-com:-blog-2013-05-09-the-y-combinator-in-six-easy-steps</id>
  <published>2013-05-09T12:43:11Z</published>
  <updated>2013-05-09T12:43:11Z</updated>
  <author>
   <name>Rommel Martinez</name></author>
  <content type="html">&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of us have been taught that to be able to define a recursive procedure, the recursive invocation must &amp;ldquo;use&amp;rdquo; the name of the recursive procedure. The &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fixed-point_combinator#Y_combinator"&gt;Y combinator&lt;/a&gt; , however, lets us perform recursion, without referring to the named identifier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Y combinator has been both a source of inspiration and frustration for many. It evokes a eureka-like sensation once you get past the wall, but it also renders us scratching our heads when it just doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to traverse the labyrinth. This post aims to bring my own approach on how to derive the Y combinator. It may not be the most elegant way, but it may work for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the code examples in this post, the &lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; symbol denotes the prompt symbol for your Scheme implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start by defining a procedure named &lt;code&gt;sum0&lt;/code&gt; that computes the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Summation"&gt;summation&lt;/a&gt; of a positive integer, down to zero. In the following snippet, the recursive call happens when &lt;code&gt;sum0&lt;/code&gt; is applied in the else part of the condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; (define sum0
    (lambda (n)
      (if (zero? n)
          0
          (+ n (sum0 (- n 1))))))
&amp;gt; (sum0 100)
5050&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have have observed that I have defined &lt;code&gt;sum0&lt;/code&gt; using an explicit &lt;code&gt;lambda&lt;/code&gt;. You&amp;rsquo;ll see shortly, why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s break that procedure futher, into more elementary components, and we&amp;rsquo;ll apply it, using &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Currying"&gt;currying&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; (define sum0
    (lambda (f)
      (lambda (n)
        (if (zero? n)
            0
            (+ n ((f f) (- n 1)))))))
&amp;gt; ((sum0 sum0) 100)
5050&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extra &lt;code&gt;lambda&lt;/code&gt; was needed because we needed to have a way to &amp;ldquo;anonymize&amp;rdquo; the recursive procedure. In this case, we used the identifier &lt;code&gt;f&lt;/code&gt; to bind to the recursive procedure, which is &lt;code&gt;sum0&lt;/code&gt;, itself. The weird-looking &lt;code&gt;((f f) ...)&lt;/code&gt; is needed, because we have to perform the same procedure invocation method used initially: &lt;code&gt;((sum0 sum0) 100)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re now going to exploit that property, to use a &amp;ldquo;nameless&amp;rdquo; approach, that is, without using the &lt;code&gt;sum0&lt;/code&gt; name.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; (((lambda (f)
      (lambda (n)
        (if (zero? n)
            0
            (+ n ((f f) (- n 1))))))
    (lambda (f)
      (lambda (n)
        (if (zero? n)
            0
            (+ n ((f f) (- n 1)))))))
   100)
5050&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take note, that at this point, we&amp;rsquo;re no longer using the &lt;code&gt;sum0&lt;/code&gt; name, to refer the the definition, except for later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we need to move the &lt;code&gt;(f f)&lt;/code&gt; part outside, to isolate the general (Y combinator), from the specific (&lt;code&gt;sum0&lt;/code&gt;) code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; (((lambda (f)
      ((lambda (p)
         (lambda (n)
           (if (zero? n)
               0
               (+ n (p (- n 1))))))
       (lambda (v) ((f f) v))))
    (lambda (f)
      ((lambda (p)
         (lambda (n)
           (if (zero? n)
               0
               (+ n (p (- n 1))))))
       (lambda (v) ((f f) v)))))
   100)
5050&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the procedure application, the identifier &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt; will be bound to &lt;code&gt;(lambda (v) ((f f) v))&lt;/code&gt;, and the identifier &lt;code&gt;v&lt;/code&gt; will be bound to &lt;code&gt;(- n 1)&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we&amp;rsquo;re going to isolate the Y combinator, from the &lt;code&gt;sum0&lt;/code&gt; procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; (((lambda (x)
      ((lambda (f)
         (x (lambda (v) ((f f) v))))
       (lambda (f)
         (x (lambda (v) ((f f) v))))))
    (lambda (p)
      (lambda (n)
        (if (zero? n)
            0
            (+ n (p (- n 1)))))))
   100)
5050&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We replace the &lt;code&gt;sum0&lt;/code&gt;-specific definition with &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt;. This requires us again, to create an enveloping &lt;code&gt;lambda&lt;/code&gt;. Since &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; is bound to the computing procedure, we no longer need to repeat it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Optionally, we can explicitly create separate procedure definitions for the Y combinator itself, and the &lt;code&gt;sum0&lt;/code&gt; procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt; (define y
    (lambda (x)
      ((lambda (f)
         (x (lambda (v) ((f f) v))))
       (lambda (f)
         (x (lambda (v) ((f f) v)))))))
&amp;gt; (define %sum0
    (lambda (p)
      (lambda (n)
        (if (zero? n)
            0
            (+ n (p (- n 1)))))))
&amp;gt; (define sum0 (y %sum0))
&amp;gt; (sum0 100)
5050&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this post has been useful in making you understand the Y combinator, currying, and procedure application. Please post your comments and suggestions, below. &amp;lt;-:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</content></entry></feed>